<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/mheab/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/mheab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-05-09T17:31:19-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mheab/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mhea Bardouille</title><subtitle>Create Caribbean RTC Internship Portfolio Page</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Telling Stories in Space and Place</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2022/02/15/telling-stories-in-place-and-time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Telling Stories in Space and Place" /><published>2022-02-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-02-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2022/02/15/telling-stories-in-place-and-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2022/02/15/telling-stories-in-place-and-time.html"><![CDATA[<style>
div {
  text-align: justify;
  text-justify: inter-word;
}

</style>

<p>In her collection of essays on the spatial humanities, Jo Guldi explains <a href="https://spatial.scholarslab.org/spatial-turn/what-is-the-spatial-turn/">spatial turn</a> and what a <a href="https://spatial.scholarslab.org/spatial-turn/the-spatial-turn-in-literature/index.html">spatial turn in literature</a> is. In the 1960s, humanities scholars spoke of a quantitative turn in history, and in 1980, a linguistic and cultural turn in history and literature. “Landscape turns” or “spatial turns” are referred to as an intellectual movement that places emphasis on place and space in social science and the humanities. Early in the development of spatial storytelling, legal scholar <a href="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Henry-Maine">Henry Maine</a>, philosopher <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernst_Cassirer">Ernst Cassirer</a>, urban historian <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lewis_Mumford">Lewis Mumford</a>, journalist <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Lippmann">Walter Lippmann</a>, and religious scholar <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mircea_Eliade">Mircea Eliade</a> were prompted to create a universal language for describing spatial experience and its artificial manipulation. After reviewing historical records, these individuals settled on the use of the words “commons,” “palimpsest,” and “pseudoenvironment.” This standardized vocabulary was critical in allowing other scholars and humanists to understand the phenomenon and create stronger arguments.</p>

<p>Spatial turns are linked to examining archival quantitative studies of history, literature, and other studies of society using digital tools to get a deeper understanding of the past or to understand how social or historical factors influence our current life. One of the digital humanities tools adapted for use in the social sciences and humanities is <a href="https://www.gislounge.com/what-is-gis/">GIS</a>. <a href="https://sis.agr.gc.ca/cansis/nsdb/cli/index.html">The Canada Land Inventory</a> developed GIS in the 1960s to reopen spatial concerns in the disciples through the use of geographical archival data. This multidisciplinary characteristic of spatial storytelling is compatible with the collaborative characteristic that is inherent in the digital humanities.</p>

<p>Guldi also explores the motions of spatial turns in literature. It all started with journalists documenting London’s urban lifestyle in order to facilitate tourism by describing crowd figures, clothing, and habits in certain neighbourhoods. It is fascinating to observe how literary representations may allow someone to imagine the appearance of a person in such depth and establish what class they belong to. After reading these papers, <a href="https://sis.agr.gc.ca/cansis/nsdb/cli/index.html">James Grant</a> became interested in how legislation affected the development of various locations in the city, including monumental architecture and political and social situations such as the presence of police. Unknowingly, through his book, <a href="https://books.google.dm/books/about/Travels_in_Town_Vol_Ii.html?id=dMqcxK1VRQYC&amp;source=kp_book_description&amp;redir_esc=y">Travels in Town (1839)</a>, Grant started to spatially tell the history of the city. Since then, there have been an enormous number of works demonstrating how a group’s location impacts its culture, ancestral forces, and imagination through the use of archive data.</p>

<p>Through our class sections, we have explored spatial turns using literature and history. Through examining archival data of different travel guides documented by foreigners, we could conclude that the unkemptness of Roseau has always been poor based on descriptions of rats, litter in the road, and comparisons to other capital cities. Thus, from understanding this history, it would be a reasonable argument to make that the cleanliness of Roseau would not improve unless a drastic social change or increased environmental awareness is made among the citizens. Furthermore, we used Google maps to spatially explain how the small portion of land in the community of Mahaut led to the formation of a clustered community, the social problems that arose, and the role Dominican Coconut Products (DCP) played in the development of the village and the creation of a middle-class society.</p>

<p>Word Count- 530 words</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="HIS115-Readings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tech Team – Jekyll</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mheab/tech-team/2022/02/13/tech-team.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tech Team – Jekyll" /><published>2022-02-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-02-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mheab/tech-team/2022/02/13/tech-team</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mheab/tech-team/2022/02/13/tech-team.html"><![CDATA[<style>
div {
  text-align: justify;
  text-justify: inter-word;
}

</style>

<p>This week, I started my work on the “Tech Team” with my first task, Jekyll. During our retreat day, we created our Jekyll pages, so I was relatively familiar with this static site generator.</p>

<p>In one of our earlier lessons with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alex_Gil_(scholar)">Alex Gil</a>, static websites were introduced to us for the first time. Simply put, static sites are folders of HTML files that are already put together and can be served up when you are visiting the site. However, dynamic sites like Amazon are created by pulling information from a database to populate a page. Since static sites are already pre-made (so there is no need to query databases), they consume less data and bandwidth than dynamic sites, which ensures that countries or individuals with fewer resources can participate in the digital humanities.</p>

<p>One of the biggest differences I have noticed between Jekyll and other content management systems (CMS) like WordPress, which I am learning about in my COMP225: Web Technologies 2 class and using to write this blog, is that Jekyll does not have a dashboard (admin UI). While this has many benefits, such as reduced admin work, there is a relatively higher learning curve. A dashboard is a lot easier to navigate, especially for less tech-savvy users who may not have interacted with the command line before or who want to memorize or remember all the codes.</p>

<p>So, this is why the “Tech Team” was created to help further the technologies we are using to create the Visualizing Caribbean Literature project.</p>

<p>My goal this week was to understand the steps needed to build a Jekyll site and how to troubleshoot any problems that may arise from this. Through my IT courses, I have learnt the importance of documentation, especially recording steps and troubleshooting methods that failed and worked for further reference. Also, reflecting on Trevor Owen’s article, <a href="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-1/please-write-it-down-by-trevor-owens/">“Please Write it Down: Design and Research in Digital Humanities,”</a> I know that every digital humanities project begins with writing.</p>

<p>Since my laptop has the necessary prerequisite instalments I started with step 2:</p>

<p><strong>STEP 2</strong>: Instal the Jekyll and the bundler gems</p>

<p>→  gem install jekyll bundler</p>

<p><br />
<img src="https://createcaribbean.org/create/cariblithistory/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2022/02/JEKYLL1.jpg" alt="Snippet of command line" />
<br /></p>

<p>Important Technical Terms:</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Gems are codes that are used to extend or modify functionality in Ruby applications. Jekyll is a gem.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Bundler is a gem that installs all the gems in your Gemfile.
<br /> <br /></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>STEP 3</strong>: Create a new Jekyll site</p>

<p>→  jekyll new (name_of_site_)
<img src="https://createcaribbean.org/create/cariblithistory/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2022/02/JEKYLL2-768x174.jpg" alt="Snippet of the error message I got. (Site name is ‘techteam’)" />
<br /></p>

<p>This was the first (of many) errors that I ran into. According to the site, <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyllrb</a>, this should have been the next step, but I was getting an error message. From retreat, I remember that a lot of the creators were also getting this message, which I believe is due to our Operating System (most of us had windows).</p>

<p>So, I consulted <a href="https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages#setting-up-jekyll-">Programming Historian</a>, which was the website we used when making our wax sites because it explained Jekyll. However, the website did not address this.</p>

<p>So, I reread <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/installation/windows/">the Jekyllrb Installation Guide for Windows</a>, and the <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/ruby-101/">Ruby 101 pages</a>, to see if I could figure out why this error was occurring, and how I could resolve it.</p>

<p>After a lot of trial and error, and re-reading these pages I was able to troubleshoot this problem.</p>

<p>Once you have installed Jekyll and the bundler gems (<strong>See Step 2</strong>):</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Install (the missing) gems in your Gemfile
      * bundle install</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Update your Ruby gems:
      * bundle update</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Create a new Jekyll site (<strong>using the  new code</strong>)
→  bundle exec jekyll new (name_of_site_)</p>

<p>Important Technical Terms:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Bundle exec allows runs the executable script needed to create the Jekyll</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="https://createcaribbean.org/create/cariblithistory/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2022/02/JEKYLL3.jpg" alt="Snippet showing the creation of the new Jekyll site (suing the new code)" />
<br /></p>

<p>Ensure that your new folder (static website) is installed in the user folder (or wherever your gemfile is)</p>

<p><strong>STEP 4</strong>: Change into your directory
→  cd (name_of_site)</p>

<p>Important Technical Terms:</p>

<ul>
  <li>CD stands for change directory (Very convenient, right?)</li>
</ul>

<p><br />
<strong>STEP 5</strong> :Build the site and make it available o
→ bundle exec Jekyll server</p>

<p><img src="https://createcaribbean.org/create/cariblithistory/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2022/02/JEKYLL14.jpg" alt="Snippet showing Steps 4 and 5" />
<br /></p>

<p>When you copy the server address or use “ http://localhost:4000/” , your Jekyll site will show!</p>

<p><img src="https://createcaribbean.org/create/cariblithistory/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2022/02/JEKYLL5.jpg" alt="My SITE was made successfully!" />
<br /></p>

<p>I am very happy that I now have a good understanding of how to build a Jekyll site. My goal for next week is to spend some time learning how to adjust the formatting features in HTML, how to create posts and gain a basic understanding of the formatting layouts.</p>

<p>Word Count: 693 words</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Tech-Team" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Library as Place, Text and Tool in Caribbean Digital Research Classrooms</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2022/02/13/the-library-as-a-place-text-tool-in-caribbean-digital-research-classroom.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Library as Place, Text and Tool in Caribbean Digital Research Classrooms" /><published>2022-02-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-02-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2022/02/13/the-library-as-a-place-text-tool-in-caribbean-digital-research-classroom</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2022/02/13/the-library-as-a-place-text-tool-in-caribbean-digital-research-classroom.html"><![CDATA[<style>
div {
  text-align: justify;
  text-justify: inter-word;
}

</style>

<p>In the article, <a href="https://schuyleresprit.com/esprit/portfolio/topography-topology-typography-the-library-as-place-text-and-tool-in-caribbean-digital-research-classrooms/">“Topography, Topology, Typography: The Library as Place, Text, and Tool in Caribbean Digital Research Classrooms,”</a> Dr Schuyler Esprit discusses her journey in creating <a href="https://createcaribbean.org/create/">Create Caribbean</a> and her interest in learning more about archives and reading patterns of the Caribbean, particularly Dominica. Through our class lessons, she has discussed certain elements of this journey and the development of her book. As a member and the current treasurer of the DSC Literary and Debating Society, one of my favourite tidbits to share is that debating societies would debate through newspapers. It is also interesting to see how this has led to the formation of the <a href="https://emonewsdm.com/dsc-students-ready-to-represent-dominica-at-the-5th-annual-windward-islands-debating-competition/?utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=dsc-students-ready-to-represent-dominica-at-the-5th-annual-windward-islands-debating-competition">Windward Islands Debating Competition</a>, for which I am one of the researchers assisting the Dominican team for the 2022 competition.</p>

<p>Moreover, although this article is 7 years old, I have been able to parallel it to my own experiences at Dominica State College. For instance, a lot of my interactions with research are usually confined to my textbooks or course outlines. Even when assignments are broadened to include Dominican or Caribbean topics, my research approaches are still limited to the Google web interface. Furthermore, the time-consuming task of locating information about Dominica due to the destruction of libraries and historical material that was not digitally preserved has made research a hated task amongst the student population.</p>

<p>In light of this, and with my experience with Create Caribbean, I believe this institution is important to integrate research techniques into digital pedagogy to explore human inquiry. Nevertheless, when I first learned about Create Caribbean, I was not sure what they did, nor how it worked, and even when I started my internship, I could not clearly see how the information and the research methodologies intersected. It was only after understanding what digital humanities was, interacting with digital humanities tools and learning, and seeing the range of projects that could be created, that my appreciation and realization of the importance of libraries, archives, and special collections grew. This medium reminds us of our distinct culture and experiences, which is particularly crucial given the widespread use of social media, which has greatly lowered interest in our culture.</p>

<p>One of my favorite classes with Dr. Esprit was when we used mapping tools to spatially explain how the small portion of land in the community of Mahaut led to the formation of a clustered community, the social problems that arose, and the role Dominica Coconut Products (DCP) played in the development of the village and the creation of a middle-class society.</p>

<p>Overall, although my interaction with libraries, archival materials, and special collections has been online, my appreciation for research has grown significantly as I have learned more about Caribbean social and cultural practices, as well as the impact slavery and colonialism have had on our daily practices and lifestyles. Moreover, I believe more students should be able to experience this, which is why technology is a great avenue to increase the knowledge of these events and assist in the digital preservation of documents.</p>

<p>Word count: 503 words</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="HIS115-Readings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Visualizing Caribbean Literary Encounters: Progress Report 4</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mheab/vcl-progress-report/2022/02/10/vcl-report-4.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visualizing Caribbean Literary Encounters: Progress Report 4" /><published>2022-02-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-02-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mheab/vcl-progress-report/2022/02/10/vcl-report-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mheab/vcl-progress-report/2022/02/10/vcl-report-4.html"><![CDATA[<style>
div {
  text-align: justify;
  text-justify: inter-word;
}

</style>

<p>When we were first given the task of conceptualizing our own digital humanities final project, I was initially scared. Although I had spent the last semester and the first two weeks of this semester learning different digital humanities tools such as GIS, and I had written two reports reflecting on digital humanities projects: <a href="http://mapping-marronage.rll.lsa.umich.edu/">Mapping Marraonge</a> and <a href="https://viraltexts.org/">The Viral Text Project</a>, I had no clue what my project would be about, or what tools I would use.</p>

<p>As a result, I decided to consult the reflective pieces I wrote when first working on the Visualizing Caribbean Literature project and <a href="http://miriamposner.com/blog/how-did-they-make-that/">Miriam Posner’s “How Did They Make That?”</a> and <a href="https://schuyleresprit.com/his115/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/What-do-digital-humanists-do.pdf">Paige Morgan’s “What Do Digital Humanists Do?”</a></p>

<p>This helped me realize two essential observations I made:</p>

<p>1) My time period was heavily dominated by male authors.</p>

<p><img src="https://createcaribbean.org/create/cariblithistory/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2022/02/T1.jpg" alt="Table 1: Female authors published during 1971-1980 of the 75 books collected" />
<br />
<em>Table 1: Female authors published during 1971-1980 of the 75 books collected</em></p>

<ul>
  <li>When Dr Esprit made a slight comment that there were a lot of men in my period of 1971–1980, I became interested in tracking the number of female authors that I came across. Although this list is incomplete (because I forgot to update it), out of the 75 books I gathered at the time, only 4 were written by female authors. Can you imagine what the number would be if I updated this list to reflect the 324 items I gathered for my section?</li>
</ul>

<p>2) There are a lot of books from certain countries.</p>

<p><img src="https://createcaribbean.org/create/cariblithistory/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2022/02/T2.jpg" alt="Table 2: Authorship by country gathered for 75 books" />
<br />
<em>Table 2: Authorship by country gathered for 75 books</em></p>

<ul>
  <li>I would expect the bigger countries in the Greater Antilles, such as Jamaica, Cuba, and Haiti, to have more published books by their respective authors because they have a larger population and more resources available. However, when I initially tracked this, I was surprised to discover that Barbados has the highest published country, whilst Haiti had one of the lowest.</li>
</ul>

<p>After gathering two potentially digital humanities topics, I started thinking about what ideas I wanted to highlight and what tools I could use. During reflection, I remembered that the synopsis of the books I read by popular male authors like V.S. Naipaul and Derek Walcott was about colonization and war, but the few female authors within my period wrote about family and love. However, the female authors I was familiar with, such as Jamaica Kincaid, whose book, “A Small Place,” I read during this time, was a long essay about Kincaid’s experience with racism in her homeland, Antigua, and how colonialism impacted Antiguan society. So, is there really a difference between what male and female authors are writing, and if so, what are they writing about? To showcase this, I decided that I could use Voyant to distant read corpuses that I could create of all the male and female authors’ books in this project to determine the main themes and ideas in their works. Furthermore, to determine why certain countries had a higher publication rate by authorship country, I could research what political, social, or economic factors existed during this time. Nevertheless, I still did not know how I could present this data in an interesting and engaging way to users. So once again, I consulted Posner and Morgan’s articles and Dr Esprit for further help.</p>

<p>Afterwards, I was able to create my initial project idea:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A semi-linear customizable narrative that includes text, images, audio, and/or video that explores the differences in the themes of works by male and female authors and determines which sex has a higher propensity to write books on specific themes such as gender and sexuality in comparison to politics. It would also contain a map to determine the geographical variances in the birth countries and publication locations of male and female authors.”
<br />
<strong>This is my intial Individual Project idea</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Although I know from <a href="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-1/what-we-think-we-will-build-and-what-we-build-in-digital-humanities-by-will-thomas/">William G. Thomas’s article “What We Think We Will Build and What We Build in Digital Humanities”</a> that what I think I will build and what I will end up building may be quite different. However, I am still very excited to explore this idea, document the process, and compile the end project with this initial idea.</p>

<p>Word Count: 655 words</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="VCL-Progress-Report" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Visualizing Caribbean Literary Encounters: Progress Report 3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mheab/vcl-progress-report/2021/12/07/vcl-report-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visualizing Caribbean Literary Encounters: Progress Report 3" /><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-12-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mheab/vcl-progress-report/2021/12/07/vcl-report-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mheab/vcl-progress-report/2021/12/07/vcl-report-3.html"><![CDATA[<style>
div {
  text-align: justify;
  text-justify: inter-word;
}

</style>

<p>This week I worked on the project “Writers, Readers, and Scenes: Visualizing Caribbean Literary Encounters.” I continued using last week’s method by searching Zotero for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Cuban_writers">Cuban</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Haitian_writers">Haitian</a> writers who were the results of a secondary Google search at the start of the week. While the results were varied and few were within my time frame, this approach increased the number of Hispanophone and Francophone authors featured in our project.</p>

<p>In addition, I looked for authors and writers in Cuba and Haiti on Wikipedia. A few of the authors listed were the same as in the Google search; however, Wikipedia also provided individuals, such as politicians and economists, who were not writers by profession, but who wrote books, doctoral dissertations, theses, and other literary works about these countries from a political or economic standpoint using the knowledge they acquired. My results from this search were mixed, and few books were published in my time period. Furthermore, from my observations, the majority of the works written by these authors were published between 1981 and 1990.</p>

<p>For the past two weeks, working on this project, I primarily used Zotero as my research tool. Thus, I decided to change my methodology this week and used the website Goodreads. I remembered remarks from prior lectures and my lecturer, Dr. Esprit’s, warning about using this website since reviews can be written by anyone and, like on Wikipedia, the data might be faulty. As a result, if two books had contradictory information, such as different publishers or different publication years, although having the same name, I would double-check the data by visiting more reputable websites.</p>

<p>Goodreads provided a more diverse list of books than Zotero, especially for lesser-known authors such as Stephen A. Dantes. Popular authors and poets, such as Edward Kamau Brathwaite, have many books published; thus, there is a multitude of information on Zotero. However, less-known authors have fewer books listed on Zotero, and research results may return authors that are not Caribbean. I have also recognized this trend in many other countries. For instance, in Jamaica, authors Andrew Salkey and Vic Reid, and Trinidadian author V.S. Naipaul, are all well-known and there is extensive information about them on Zotero.</p>

<p>This begs the question in my mind, “What factors caused the popularization of books by certain authors in the Caribbean during my period?” Can it be attributed to the themes and materials presented in these works, or was it due to the advertising of publishers? This is an interesting perspective on which I could base my reflective piece.</p>

<p>Our other classes working with Zotero, as well as the class with Alex Gil, are helping me to better understand how this digital humanities project will be created. Although there will be challenges, I am very excited about what lies ahead.</p>

<p>465 words</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="VCL-Progress-Report" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Visualizing Caribbean Literary Encounters: Progress Report 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mheab/vcl-progress-report/2021/11/30/vcl-report-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visualizing Caribbean Literary Encounters: Progress Report 2" /><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-11-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mheab/vcl-progress-report/2021/11/30/vcl-report-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mheab/vcl-progress-report/2021/11/30/vcl-report-2.html"><![CDATA[<style>
div {
  text-align: justify;
  text-justify: inter-word;
}

</style>

<p>This week I continued working on the project “Writers, Readers, and Scenes: Visualizing Caribbean Literary Encounters”. At the start of the week, I used the same method of searching for authors I knew on Zotero and clipping books published into their respective folders using the browser extension. However, I soon ran into a dead end because I could not recall any more authors off the top of my head. I then remembered that many of the books were written by different authors, so I searched for books published by these co-authors. This provided me with many different types of literature. However, very few were in my time range. Furthermore, I noticed that a lot of anglophone Caribbean authors would collaborate with American authors, Hispanophone authors would collaborate with authors from Spain, and francophone authors with authors born in France. Therefore, I could not use the books published by these individuals as our project defined “Caribbean literature” as literature written by individuals born in Caribbean countries.</p>

<p>So, I decided to review the metadata I had for the books in my folder. As seen in my <a href="https://createcaribbean.org/create/cariblithistory/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/Authorship-by-Country.jpg">“Progress Report 1” table 1</a>, a lot of the books I found were by Anglophone authors and were heavily concentrated in a few countries. Therefore, I needed a new strategy. I went on Wikipedia and searched for Caribbean countries, and was given a list of the different <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Caribbean_countries_by_population">Caribbean countries by population</a>. Using each country on this list, I did a secondary search on Google for authors born in that country. Then I would search on Zotero for any books published by these authors within my time range and the other ranges.</p>

<p>This week I searched for authors in Cuba and Haiti. The results of this were varied. While I got more literature written by Hispanophone and Francophone authors, many of the results would not refer to my time period or the authors were not born in these countries but wrote about events that occurred in them. Hence, I had to continuously double-check through a Google search or on Wikipedia for the birth country of each unknown author.</p>

<p>My work on my individual part of the project highlighted how I may need to do multiple different searches to obtain books within my time period, as well as the significance of staying vigilant, because not all the books meet my criteria.</p>

<p>We also had a class with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alex_Gil_(scholar)">Mr Alex Gil</a> this week to explain minimal computing and Wax, which is focused on providing flexible, low-cost websites that are long-lasting. Dr Esprit also explained how the metadata collected from each book will be exported as a CSV file, which is needed to build the wax site. So, I plan to spend a few hours next week verifying that the information in the metadata for each book is correct and fill out the missing sections.</p>

<p>475 words</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="VCL-Progress-Report" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Visualizing Caribbean Literary Encounters: Progress Report 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mheab/vcl-progress-report/2021/11/23/vcl-report-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visualizing Caribbean Literary Encounters: Progress Report 1" /><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-11-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mheab/vcl-progress-report/2021/11/23/vcl-report-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mheab/vcl-progress-report/2021/11/23/vcl-report-1.html"><![CDATA[<style>
div {
  text-align: justify;
  text-justify: inter-word;
}

</style>

<p>This week we worked on the project “Writers, Readers, and Scenes: Visualizing Caribbean Literary Encounters”. In this project, my task is to locate all literature written by Caribbean authors between 1971 and 1980 and store the metadata related to these works in Zotero. Our previous classes explaining how to use Zotero’s app, browser extension, and other functionalities have streamlined this process for me. Working with metadata has also given me a better understanding of how this information helps manage resources and retrieve documents, which were introduced to me in previous weekly readings.</p>

<p>I find the adage “Don’t judge a book by its cover” ironic since that is exactly what I have been doing for the past few days when gathering different books and reading their synopses. To accomplish my task, I initially did a broad search of “Caribbean authors” on different sites like Goodreads or Amazon. However, this proved to be inefficient because my results would include elements not directly relating to my objective, like authors who were not born in the Caribbean or who wrote books about Caribbean authors or literature, whereas I wanted the original publication of these works.</p>

<p>Therefore, I changed my strategy to include keywords in my searches to narrow my results. This provided me with more appropriate results, but I quickly realized that commercial sites like Amazon or Goodreads did not have the data I wanted. So, I started to use “Worldcat” and “Digital Library of the Caribbean,” which are digital archives that preserve documents and ensure there is open access to them. I also began searching for specific Caribbean authors that I knew, such as Kamau Brathwaite and Derek Walcott, and others provided to me by Dr. Esprit, like Dionne Brand and George Lamming. This method has proved to be the most effective so far.</p>

<p>My individual work on this project has developed my research skills, as I have learnt how to better manipulate my searches to get the results I want.</p>

<p>There are also a few topics I am interested in exploring that I could base my reflective piece on. For example, I have observed in this time period that a lot of the literature is from authors born in Barbados, Jamaica, or Trinidad and Tobago.</p>

<p><img src="https://createcaribbean.org/create/cariblithistory/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/Authorship-by-Country.jpg" alt="Table 1; Authorship by country collected for 75 books" />
<br />
<em>Table 1; Authorship by country collected for 75 books</em></p>

<p>Therefore, my personal project could focus on the economic and social factors in these countries that contributed to the increase in published work.</p>

<p>Furthermore, as Dr Espirt points out, there aren’t as many female authors during this time period. Therefore, I have chosen to keep a record of all female writers who published books in 1971 and 1980.</p>

<p><img src="https://createcaribbean.org/create/cariblithistory/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/Female-Authors.jpg" alt="Table 2: Female authors" />
<br />
<em>Table 2: Female authors</em></p>

<p>A possible angle my personal project could explore is the different themes of topics written by female and male authors using distant reading tools like Voyant. Even though I may not create projects on these topics, I think they are interesting subtopics that can help broaden my personal understanding.</p>

<p>Word Count – 480 words</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="VCL-Progress-Report" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Digital History?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2021/11/16/what-is-digital-history.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Digital History?" /><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-11-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2021/11/16/what-is-digital-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2021/11/16/what-is-digital-history.html"><![CDATA[<style>
div {
  text-align: justify;
  text-justify: inter-word;
}

</style>

<p>The World Wide Web (www) and web browsers, as well as technological advancements, have transformed the way we read and process information. This global information network has not only increased the amount of open-source material available to students, allowing them to access primary sources in previously inconceivable ways, but it has also revolutionized research processes and tools. Digital history is the use of computer tools, software systems, and networked information to evaluate, portray, and depict historical research findings. It’s not just about digitizing the past; it’s about building a framework for humanists to employ code, tools, and software, as well as existing technology, to create new ways of conducting humanities studies that the general public can read and experience.</p>

<p>Many researchers struggled to distinguish between digitization projects and digital history scholarship throughout the early phases of the field’s popularization. However, a clear distinction can be made today. Digitization is more widespread both within and outside academia and involves making collections available in digital form. Digital history projects, on the other hand, organize a more distinct collection of sources and resources around a historiographical topic. The “Mapping Marrongae” initiative, which I examined recently, is an example of a digital history project. This project aimed to investigate the numerous ways slaves attempted to emancipate themselves by mapping the movements and correspondences shown in different bodies of work. As a result, the resources such as manumission papers, letters, and biographies are all organized to answer this major research question. The researchers also made these documents available in a digital format, whether through OCR scanned photos (PDF) or using text encoding initiative (TEI) to encode the textual content. Therefore, as illustrated, many digital projects have a great deal of digitizing as part of their work, but the focus is different from other organizations.</p>

<p>Furthermore, collaboration is an essential component of digital history projects. In a previous reading, “What We Think We Will Build and What We Build in Digital Humanities,” Williams provided an example of a possible way digital humanists collaborate or form partnerships with libraries to create models, preserve, and make the scholarship research from digital humanities and interpretive archives available to the wider public. To create digital history projects, teamwork is not only required with librarians but also with technology professionals and historians. Even in the digital history project that my class is working on, cross-collaboration is evident as some students are in information technology or computer science majors, and others are perusing business and geography majors.</p>

<p>The future of digital history is to shift the focus from the product-oriented or “website” to process-oriented work by employing new media tools in research and analysis. To do this, the data in digital history has to be considered a scholarly product. For this to happen, the challenges of the quality of data, as well as preservation of data and open access to content, need to be addressed. Digital preservation and open access are some of the broad categories of digital humanities that would ensure that literature is available to humanists without having to pay for it, and these resources can be turned into a digitization project to enable this historical knowledge to be available to the general public in the future. Additionally, quality of data refers to transforming “big data” that is unstructured, messy and heterogeneous into “smart data” through the use of analysis of computational tools to reduce as many imperfections as possible. Digital history projects can only be created if these three elements are met.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="HIS115-Readings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Curation as Publishing for the Humanities</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2021/10/19/data-curation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Curation as Publishing for the Humanities" /><published>2021-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2021/10/19/data-curation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2021/10/19/data-curation.html"><![CDATA[<style>
div {
  text-align: justify;
  text-justify: inter-word;
}

</style>

<p>When I think of publishing, I think of preparing and distributing physical products, such as books, journals, and newspapers, for the public to read for free or for a fee. However, digitalization has revolutionized the nature of publishing, allowing authors to develop and disseminate digital works on platforms like Joomag or WordPress. It has also altered how digital humanists create, disseminate, and exchange data for publication.  Digital humanities have had to add new aspects to their concepts of “publication”, namely data curation due to the interaction of theory, data and computation methods in digital humanities scholarship.</p>

<p>The active and continuous management of data throughout its lifecycle of relevance and utility to scholarship, science, and education is known as data curation. Data curation is simply preparing, collecting, organizing and maintaining datasets. A dataset is a logically organized collection of data related to a specific body of work or subject. Datasets can be itemized and can be quantitative, qualitative, or visual images and audio. My transcript on the Dominica  State College, Orbund platform, which is the student information system (SIS) used, is an example of a dataset I engage with on a weekly basis. This dataset contains quantitative data on my course grades and attendance for each semester. Other individuals would interact with data curation when attending exhibits in museums.</p>

<p>By linking data curation and publishing, digital humanists ensure that curated data is as legible as published work. It can therefore be reused to enable data discovery and the creation of new digital humanities projects that visualise our experience and enable data retrieval.</p>

<p>During class, Dr Esprit showed us the dataset curated for the digital humanities project, Cariseland, which was built in collaboration with previous interns. This itemized information dataset contained the data and metadata necessary to develop the project and was created and populated in an excel spreadsheet. This was also an example of how data curation and datasets enable the retrieval of data, since if the data was not arranged it could not have been retrieved during class.</p>

<p>However, curating datasets like these and larger ones undoubtedly takes a lot of time, effort, and money. Nonetheless, digital humanists and organizations recognize the value of these datasets to ensure the open access of knowledge to the general public, and to allow other humanists the ability to reuse this data in their initiatives.</p>

<p>Thus, by recognising data curation work as a publishing activity, libraries would see the business opportunity and collaborate with digital humanities. Therefore, organizations will have both a “back end” (librarian) and a “front end” (publisher) to help preserve and distribute scholarly publications. Publishers add value to finished products through peer review and high-quality production and presentation, whereas libraries standardize these works while expanding open access.</p>

<p>So, businesses that include both a library and a publisher can envision this as a cohesive package of services covering the complete data lifecycle. Data can be compiled, cleaned of impurities, arranged and curated to present a story, and mined using computational approaches to build digital humanities projects.</p>

<p>Word Count – 504 Words</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="HIS115-Readings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data in Humanities and Data Management</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2021/10/12/data-in-humanities-and-data-management.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data in Humanities and Data Management" /><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2021/10/12/data-in-humanities-and-data-management</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mheab/his115-readings/2021/10/12/data-in-humanities-and-data-management.html"><![CDATA[<style>
div {
  text-align: justify;
  text-justify: inter-word;
}

</style>

<p>In IT, I’ve always been taught that data is unprocessed information or raw facts. Even in my accounting studies, I collect and record data from various financial transactions, which I then analyze and compute to generate information. For example, an amount of $1,000,000 in the sales ledger by itself has little meaning to me, managers, or company owners. However, through computation and analysis, I can utilize this number and other elements of data in the accounting cycle to determine figures like profit and loss, which may aid forecasting and decision-making.</p>

<p>Nonetheless, “data” in humanities is not a discrete, fungible unit on which one can conduct operations to generate an outcome. So this bears the question of what exactly is data in the humanities?</p>

<p>Digital data, at its fundamental level, is binary (1s and 0s) and can be represented in linear, hierarchical, or multi-relational structures such as arrays, XML files, and graph-based databases.</p>

<p>Structured, semi-structured, and unstructured data can all be found in the humanities field. In a database, structured data consists of key-value pairs in which unique primary keys identify and manage other values in a record, making retrieval easier. Data in XML files is considered semi-structured data. Despite my unfamiliarity with this markup language, my prior knowledge of HTML has helped me to understand how the concept of tags is used in XML, like HTML, to markup a document and identify logical structures such as chapters, headers, and paragraphs. Through my studies of Digital Humanities, I have now been able to understand that markup used in XML, and HTML is comparable to annotating a book with a pen or using the ‘track changes tool in Microsoft Word.</p>

<p>Structured and unstructured data can both be categorized as “smart” data, provided they are clean and limited in volume. In digital data, the term “clean” refers to minimizing any flaws in the collection process. Additionally, smart data includes raw data, markup, annotations, and metadata. Since these elements are individually created, smart data is limited in volume due to the time-intensive work. Furthermore, smart data is governed by the Text Encoding Initiative, which I think to be one of the most confusing and difficult elements of the broad classifications of humanities, and I believe might be one of the reasons for smart data’s limited amount.</p>

<p>Finally, unstructured data, as the name indicates, is disorganized and does not follow a certain schema or structure, such as the body of an email. Unstructured data, also known as big data, is vast in volume, diversified, and produced continually by sensors or as a by-product of people’s actions.</p>

<p>These classifications have given me a better understanding of what data is in the humanities. So, to answer the question, data in the humanities can be digital, but it must reflect some component or object of humanistic research such as history, art, philosophy, or literature. It is selectively created and developed using features such as markup, annotations, and metadata. It includes humanists using cultural artefacts like books to comprehend another culture or timeline, or literary academics using knowledge of other eras and cultures to create the meaning of a text using digital technologies.</p>

<p>The increased digitization of data in the humanities has increased the need for data management technologies, such as Zotero, a bibliographic and citation management application. Whilst using Zotero, I saw the collaborative function by joining a group for a digital humanities class to share resources. This also enables open access to content as people can view other humanities research findings. Lastly, Zotero uses metadata, thereby ensuring there is digital preservation of historical knowledge and information.</p>

<p>600 words</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="HIS115-Readings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>